<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Englands ioy, for suppressing the papists, and banishing the priests and Iesuites</title>
            <author>Scott, Thomas, 1580?-1626.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A73135</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22076</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100080</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99900599</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99900599</idno>
            <idno type="VID">177959</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A73135)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177959)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1291:20; 2033:12; 2084:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Englands ioy, for suppressing the papists, and banishing the priests and Iesuites</title>
                  <author>Scott, Thomas, 1580?-1626.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 16 p   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Nicholas Okes?],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London?] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M. DC. XXIV. [1624]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Thomas Scott.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 22076a at reel 1291:20.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of originals in: Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.) Library, Harvard University Library and the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177959:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177959:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ENGLANDS IOY, FOR SVPPRESSING the Papiſts, and baniſhing the <hi>Prieſts and Ieſuites.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 KING. 18.21.</hi>
               </bibl> How long hault yee betweene two opinions? If the Lord be God, then follow him; if Ball, then follow him.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 KING. 17.24, 25.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>And the King of Aſſyria brought men from Babylon, and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow Cuthah, and from Aua, and from Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, and from Sepharuaim, and placed them in the Cities of Samaria, in ſtead of the children of Iſrael, and they poſseſſed Samaria, and dwelt in the Cities thereof.</p>
               <p>And ſo it was at the beginning of their dwelling there, that they feared not the Lord: Therefore the Lord ſent Lyons among them, which ſlew ſome of them.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed <hi>M.DC.XXIV.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:177959:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:177959:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>ENGLANDS IOY, FOR SVPPRESSING of Papiſtry, and baniſhing <hi>the Prieſts and Ieſuites.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Confeſſe that prayer is ſo forcible, that it openeth the gates of heauen; and as you read, how the holy Ghoſt deſcended vpon the Apoſtles in the forme of fiery tongues, ſo through the enforcement of Prayer, all bleſſings ſpirituall and temporall are let downe amongſt the children of God, like <hi>Peters</hi> ſheete. Who would not then aske to obtaine? ſeeke to finde? knocke to haue it opened? and importune the father of mercy to haue no deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all? conſidering the Parable tells vs, That the wicked Iudge who neither feared God nor man, granted the widowes Petition to be deliuered from her clamors, and ouer troubleſome attendancy? and thus are wee beholding to our God.</p>
            <p>But now, to make God beholding vnto vs, were a ſecret out of the Treaſure-houſe of heauen indeed, wherein I will be bould to tell you how you may be proficient, and inuite you to wiſdomes ſchoole to learne a cunning which the heart of the naturall man is vncapable of; and this is, to retribute thankes to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:177959:3"/> God, to giue his glorious name the praiſe, to bee gratefull vnto him, and to reioyce in hymnes and ſpirituall Songs when a benefit is imparted, and our ſoules are comforted.</p>
            <p>What a ſtory is the ſtory of the Iewes, being deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered from <hi>Hamans</hi> cruelty and perſecution, for the purpoſe in hand.<note place="margin">Heſter 9.17, 18</note> The Text ſaith; That they reſted the ſame day, and made it a day of feaſting and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, a good day, and ſent portions and preſents one to another: but wherefore was all this? For ſauing their liues, and preuailing againſt their enemies.</p>
            <p>But, oh thou God of heauen! that rideſt vpon the wings of the winde, and holdeſt the reynes of the kingdomes of the world in thy hand, to let looſe or reſtraine at thy pleaſure: Thou knoweſt that we haue more cauſes to reioyce and bee glad then the Iewes in their Parim. For, if wee may compare the leſſe with the greater, they had but the preſeruation of their bodies, and a ſlight tryumph againſt their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall enemies, we are in the way to ſaue our ſoules, and put our ſpirituall aduerſaries to flight, the Fleſh, the World, and the Diuell.</p>
            <p>What? Papiſtrie to be ſuppreſſed? The Prieſts and Ieſuites to be baniſhed? And the Goſpell of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt to flouriſh?<note place="margin">Pſalme 45.</note> My ſoule leapes for joy, and my heart is enditing a good matter. I ſpeake of the things which I haue made touching the King, my tongue is the pen of a ready writer. Oh bleſsed be God for this alteration?</p>
            <p>Doth not <hi>Ieremy</hi> tell vs, that, <hi>In Ramah there was a voyce heard,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ieremy 31. Math. 2.</note> 
               <hi>lamentation, and weeping, and great mourning, Rachell weeping for her children, and would
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:177959:3"/> not be comforted becauſe they were not.</hi> Did not al <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> wring their hands for ſorrow, and begin to mourne and be affrighted, when they ſaw the Papiſts ſo arrogantly miſchieuous, to inſult in euery towne and ſhire, and mocke vs to our faces, as if <hi>Sandolet</hi> and <hi>Tobiah</hi> were to ſcoffe and deride the Iewes, when <hi>Nehemiah</hi> came to re-edifie the Temple. And hath not God put into the Kings heart to dam vp this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>undation, and to keepe the raging Sea within limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, that it doe not ouerflow the lower and fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full grounds.</p>
            <p>Marke but the progreſſion of buſineſſe, tell it to your Children, and write it in the Philacteries of your garments. Did not we determin to match with <hi>Spaine?</hi> And did not <hi>Spaine</hi> reſolue to ouermatch vs in the contract? Did he not reſemble an vnmanner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and impudent Gueſt, who inuited to ſome neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourly meeting, would not onely come himſelfe, but brought a whole rablement of Cormorants with him: ſo <hi>Spaine</hi> muſt not only condition for a daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but the Papiſts through the Kingdome haue li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Conſcience, Maſſe in their houſes, Prieſts within their doores, penalties remitted, and the Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuants and Officers reſtrained from their priuy ſearches, whereby the Spaniſh Ambaſſadour preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med on his meritorious ſeruice, and ſome Papiſts tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphed, as if the wiſer ſort knew they were in the right. And was not this a fearefull beginning, and who knowes with what ſtrength the ſtrong man would haue encreaſed in keeping his poſſeſſion.</p>
            <p>But was this all? No, no, the ſeuerall ſhiers of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> worſe then the Iewes that poyſoned the ſprings
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:177959:4"/> of ſweet water, in theſe daies had malitious inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to corrupt the youth of the Countrey, and the Prieſts, Ieſuites and Friers ranne from houſe to houſe, and made them all amazed with crying out; <hi>Great is Diana of the Epheſians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now Papiſtry ſhall be ſuppreſſed, and the Prieſts and Ieſuites baniſhed. Oh bleſſed alteration: oh bleſſed King: oh bleſſed Parliament. The Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors houſes were ſo many hiues to which the drones reſorted, who not onely fed vpon the hony of the Bees, but preſumed to kill and beat them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way which preſerued them: Thus theſe vnconſtant people, not onely deſpiſed the Paſtors of their own Congregations, and vnder protection of the Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue of Kings, rayled on the Lord and his annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. The Streets ſwarmed with ruffianly appariti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Prieſts in diſguiſed apparell, and Ieſuites in Courtly veſtments. And what did they? Not only watch the outward behauiour of men, and gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the City, but tooke aduantage of the weak carnall Goſpeller, and ſet vpon them with the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward glory of a viſſible Church.</p>
            <p>The Cathedrall of Paules had her walkes min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with a number of peremptory and audatious Romaniſts, who not onely brandeth vs for luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmneſs and vniuſtifiable actions, but boaſted both of and in their diſputations, that they had put the true and learned ſeruants of God to ſilence, as if <hi>Zedchiah</hi> ſhould ſtrike <hi>Michaiah</hi> on the face, and peremptorily aske him, when the Spirit of God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from him, to bee infuſed into ſuch an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derling.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:177959:4"/>
            <p>The Court hath not onely euery corner, but pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke walkes filled with Papiſts, and Hiſpaniolized temporiſers. And what did they? appeare in ſeuerall diſguiſed formes, and their corrupt hearts taught their tongues to vent forth blaſphemy, and notori-abuſes: For as you read how <hi>Ieremy</hi> was taken by his enemies, and brought before the Princes and Prieſts for weakning the hands of the men of warre, and daunted their hearts that wiſhed well to the peace of <hi>Zion:</hi> So played theſe impoſturing ſpirits, charming all men with ſuch ſubtilties. What? the houſe <hi>Auſtria</hi> to be checked, and the Emperour of <hi>Germany</hi> to be affronted with petty rebels? beleeue it not it is impoſſible, take heed, how you aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in ſuch a buſineſſe; you ſee how hee preuailes, and no forces can reſiſt him. What? the Arch-Dutches to be mated with ſuch inferiors, traytors, rebells, and mechanicke vpſtarts? Neuer ſpeake it for ſhame: For at this inſtant they are no leſſe then foure mighty armies, 60000 men ready to deuoure theſe one night Muſhrumps, and ſetting vpon their terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories in foure places at once, make a fatall ruine of all their fortunes and hopes in a moment.</p>
            <p>What? <hi>Spaine</hi> to be threatned with warre, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſions of hoſtillity? Who is able to couer the <hi>Viena,</hi> as <hi>Xerxes</hi> once did the <hi>Helleſpont,</hi> with a numberleſſe, and inuincible Armado, to ſet vpon the Iland of <hi>Brittany</hi> as a Conqueror: to trouble <hi>Ireland</hi> with an army of 20000: to infeſt <hi>Scotland,</hi> and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>run it at pleaſure, and to make <hi>England</hi> to tremble with the multitude of his forces, and yet dare you talke of warre and aſſiſting the Low-Countries? But
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:177959:5"/> now God be thanked, Papiſtry ſhall be ſuppreſſed, the Prieſts and Ieſuits baniſhed, and theſe mighty Buls of <hi>Baſſan</hi> either haue their hornes ſawed off, or their chaps mufled, and what an alteration is heere?</p>
            <p>Oh let vs then giue thankes vnto God, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe his mercy is beyond our apprehenſion, and his benefits are an <hi>Ocean</hi> in compariſon of our duty, ſtanding poole of deſeruing. And ſeeing the King is ſo gracious to looke vpon vs like a faire mouing Planet, in a conſpicuous <hi>Orbe,</hi> from whoſe influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence can proceede nothing but ſweet preſages: See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Parliament is ſo religiouſly Honorable, to ſound the foord of <hi>Spaines</hi> proiects, and their fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries haſſard by colluſion, and halting betweene two opinions: with the plummets of true Wiſedome, and Zeale to the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt: Seeing our Clergy are ſo indulgent ouer Gods Church, that they will not ſuffer either the wild Bore of the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt to trample downe the hedges, or little Foxes to deſtroy the Grapes, but are willing that <hi>Iehoydas</hi> filthy garments may be taken away, and a crowne of pure Gold ſet vpon his head, ſeeing the people are prepared to call and haſten one another to go vp to the Temple of the Lord; and rather then <hi>Ruben</hi> ſhall rayſe a heape of ſtones like an Alter, to put the people in feare of Idolatry, they are ready to arme with their brethren, and examine how the matter ſtands, let euery man exhillerat himſelfe, and cry out: <hi>Why art thou cast downe ô my ſoule, and why art thou diſquieted within me? hope thou in God, for I ſhall yet praiſe him, he is the health of my countenance, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:177959:5"/> my God:</hi> So then if Papiſtry ſhall be ſuppreſſed, the Prieſts and Ieſuites baniſhed, and our enemies, both Forraine and Domeſticke ouer-reached: let God haue the glory, the Prince the honor, the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the commendation, the people the comfort, the Country the benefit, and euery true hearted Chriſtian ſing <hi>Iopaean,</hi> and <hi>Epithalamians</hi> to <hi>Iehouah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Marke the difference betweene flouriſhing King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes through the bleſſing of reformation, and aduiſe of good gouernours, and the fearefull diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Common-wealths, where irreligion and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>direct courſes ouer-maiſter: While the ambition of <hi>Athalia</hi> was predominant ouer her affection, and driue her head-long to al voſcenity and tyranny, ſhe committed idolatry, ſhe neglected the houſe of God, ſhe defiled the Alter, ſhe deſtroyed the ſeed-royal, ſhe vſurped the Diadem, and diſturbed the peace of <hi>Iuda</hi> and <hi>Iſrael:</hi> But when <hi>Iehoas</hi> was miraculouſly preſerued and inſtructed by <hi>Iehoiada: Athalia</hi> is ſlaine: <hi>Iehoaſh</hi> doth that which is right in ſight of God, the Prieſts repaire the Temple, the Alters are cleanſed, the Common-wealth reformed, and the whole Country reſetled in order; and was not this a great alteration?</p>
            <p>In the ſtory of <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> and <hi>Ammon</hi> his ſonne, you ſhall finde theſe imputations of wickedneſſe caſt vpon them by the Holy Ghoſt: Hee did that which was euill in the ſight of the Lord, hee liued after the abhominations of the Heathen, hee reared vp Alters for <hi>Baal,</hi> he offred incenſe to the Hoſt of Heauen, he made his ſonne paſſe through the fire, he vſed enchauntments, obſerue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> times, and dealt with familiar ſpirits, and wrought much wickednes
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:177959:6"/> before the Lord: But when <hi>Ioſiah</hi> came to raine, and was inſtructed how? he feared God, and liued vprightly, he cleanſed and repayred the Temple: he commanded the booke of God to be read, hee rent his cloathes as ſtrucken with compunction of ſoule, he made a couenant with God to obſerue his teſtimonies, hee put downe all the offices of <hi>Baal,</hi> and the groues dedicated vnto him: Hee ſlew his Prieſts, he ſolemnized the Paſſeouer, and he perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the words of the Law, which were written in the Booke; and was not this a great alteration?</p>
            <p>Thus is it betweene the gouernment of <hi>Spaine</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> eſpecially the contrariety of Religion, and diuerſity of ſeruing God, betweene Papiſts and Proteſtants: the Papiſts both in <hi>Spaine</hi> and in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> commit blaſphemous idolatry, are poluted with inceſts and fornication, derogate from the Honor of God, to attribute adoration to creatures, paſſifieth himſelf in the Laborynth of aequiuocation: Diſſemble with God, their owne ſoules, and all that deale with them, care not by what meanes or treachery they compaſſe their owne ends, deny Chriſts preſence in Heauen, a maine article of Faith, extenuate the power of the God-head, by allowing a dyety to Creatures, and an inuocation to Diuells. Firſt, they haue made many Saints that are paſſed downe to Hell: Allow of murther and monſtrous impiety, and in a word, are poyſoned with the dregs of abhomination, wherewith the whore of <hi>Babi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> hath filled her cup.</p>
            <p>The true Proteſtant and zealous Chriſtian allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth God the preheminence of all adoration, will by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o meanes blaſpheme with idolatrous exorciſmes,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:177959:6"/> deteſteth whoredome, and all inceſtuous Leproſie, defieth the participation of Gods glory to murther, ſimply and plainly contriueth his affaires, and kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth his word, though it be to his owne hinderance, intermeddles not with matters of ſtate, except hee be called to place of eminency, is with <hi>Anna</hi> pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Temple, and continually reioyceth in the conuerſation of Gods ſeruants, and maketh the Church the ſanctuary of his ſoule, in a word, is ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the directory of Gods word, and neither dare abuſe the Maieſty of Princes by inter-iecting a iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie and ſuſpition betweene the Prince and the ſubiect, nor runne away with the deceit of his owne heart, in preſuming to be more holy then his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, or preiudging others either maliciouſly, or fooliſhly: And is not this a great alteration? And is not this cauſe enough to compell vs to thanke God, and acknowledge his mercy and kindneſſe, that our King and Parliament would goe and buy eye-ſalue without money, perſpicuouſly to looke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the enormities of the Church and Common-wealth, and not onely with <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> abridged the extreamity of vſury: compelled a relaxation of debts and oppreſſion, kept and ſanctified the Sabba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oth,<note place="margin">Nehemiah 13.</note> droue the Merchants and ſellers of meate out of the City, and at laſt put away their idolatrous wiues: but alſo would not ſuffer the <hi>Ammonites</hi> and <hi>Moabites</hi> to come into Gods Temple, but enforced them to baniſhment out of <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For as you read how <hi>Iacob</hi> after his returne from <hi>Laban</hi> cleanſed his houſe of the idols: ſo did <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> in deſpight of <hi>Eliaſhib</hi> the Prieſt, who had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied himſelfe to <hi>Tobiah</hi> a ſtranger and idolater, put
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:177959:7"/> him from his lodging, and caſt out all the ſtuffe out of his chamber, which in the text is likewiſe called cleanſing, and thus thankes be to God, our great <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemiah</hi> dealt with the Papiſts, hee hath not onely thought them as prickes and thornes in the ſides of good Chriſtians: but now found them as noyſome and infectious weedes in the Common-wealth, to choake and eate vp the ſweeter Flowers, and ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing graſſe; and thus hath the Church of God ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample enough in Scripture to be an enemy to Gods enemies, and fall to reformation with courage and magnamity.</p>
            <p>Shall ſuch a man as I flye, (ſayth <hi>Nehemiah</hi>) ſhall ſuch a King as I, (ſayth King <hi>Iames</hi>), that haue been trayned vp from my infancy to deny Popery, and for my Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> a very nurſery of zealous profeſſors, and mirrour of purity and piety, ſuffer <hi>England</hi> to be defiled and contaminated with the poyſon of ſuperſtition; &amp; now I haue recollected my ſelfe, ſhall I giue way to rotten and filthy policy, to eate vpon the heart of true Religion, or ſuffer pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate ends to thicken themſelues, like ſome obſcure and dangerous cloud, to ſtand as an interpoſition betweene the Sunny ſplendor of Gods word, and the faire progreſſe of gouerment: No, No? I will now be my ſelfe, and therefore if either the Pope or <hi>Spaine</hi> deride me with <hi>Michol</hi> for dancing before the Arke, and bringing it in into Gods houſe: I will anſwere with <hi>Dauid,</hi> I will yet bee more vilde and zealous for the Lord; and as he told his wife, that therefore God had taken the Kingdome from her father, and inueſted him with the Diadem, ſo may King <hi>Iames</hi> anſwere <hi>Spaine,</hi> that therefore God will
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:177959:7"/> make him mighty in his Prouinces, in deſpight of malignant oppoſition, and <hi>England</hi> ſhall not be on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly able to ſtand firme, like an impregnable rocke in all honor, riches, and proſperity: but of ſufficiency to protect diſtreſſed neighbours, and recouer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate and ſurrepted Prouinces: Therefore away yee Prieſts and Ieſuites, packe hence for your liues; and let me not heare any further of your daring im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtures, and you that will remaine Papiſts, and with the Adder ſtoppe your eares, that charme the Charmer neuer ſo cunningly, hee ſhall not preuaile ro remoue you, take heede and bee warned, that you liue modeſtly in your wilfulneſſe, neither daring to breake our ſtatutes againſt thoſe Locuſts of <hi>Rome,</hi> nor to inſult your ſelues, or be offenſiue to any ciuill conuerſaſion by the wrong defence and ſupportation of <hi>Romes</hi> corrupted Doctrine: For I proteſt vnto you by the faith of a Religious King, I take a pleaſure in hearing, what God ſayd to <hi>Abraham:</hi> For I know him, that he will command his children,<note place="margin">Geneſis 18.19</note> and his houſhold after him, and they ſhall keepe the way of the Lord to doe iuſtice and iudgment, that the Lord may bring vpon <hi>Abraham</hi> that which hee hath ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vnto him: And therefore as I am Gods ſubſtitute in the ſupreame royalty, ſo will I be his inſtrument in the practiſe of this reformation, neither ſuffring any Papiſt whatſoeuer to haue the vſe of Idolatrous maſſes, nor to bring vp their owne Children in the eimerian darkneſſe of ignorance, and diueliſh deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: For the Apoſtle tells vs plainely,<note place="margin">Coloſ. 2.</note> that the tormenting the body, worſhipping of Angells, obſeruing of Dayes, and many fooliſh humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, likewiſe denying of lawfull marriage, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:177959:8"/> forbidding of meates, and cellebrating of ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious times, are all the doctrines of the Diuell: and is not this joy to <hi>England,</hi> and how are our hearts cheered, as you read of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> that in the time of <hi>Salomon</hi> reioyced with one another, and made merry eating and drinking vnder ther owne Vines.</p>
            <p>Thus ſhall wee ſee the backes of our aduerſaries, and by Gods ſpeciall fauour and grace the baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Prieſts, and Ieſuits: But yee Maieſtrates of the Common-wealth? let them not immitate the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi> in this,<note place="margin">Exod 40.</note> to rob the <hi>Egyptians</hi> in their departure out of <hi>Egypt?</hi> Let them not exporte our treaſures, nor enrich other Countries with our ſpoyles: Let not your Ladies beſtow their iewels and ornaments vpon them: For though they could be contented to loue them with gratuities and preſents, yet muſt the Common-wealth reſerue ſome ſecrets of State, not to be impoueriſhed by the lauiſh gifts of thoſe, that vnderſtand not the Miſtery of carying wealth out of the Land, or conſuming our ſiluer in trifles, let none of their houſes bee furniſhed with thoſe rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants of gew-gawes, wherein the ancient idolaters excelled them in be decking their idols, I meane their meduies, crucifixes, relickes of ſaints, the wood of the Croſſe, the milke of our Lady, and a thouſand ſuch like trumperies fit for nothing but toyes to play with all, as Apes do with Nut-ſhells: For as you read how the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were tainted with the groſſe ſuperſtition of <hi>Egypt:</hi> ſo muſt needes the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hearts of your women be captiuated with the reſeruation of theſe things: Let your Purſeuants and Officers a Gods name be the reſearchers of ſuſpected
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:177959:8"/> places, that the very children, which as yet, know no harme, may be ſent to the Schooles of the children of the Prophets, and by that meanes learne to liue in the feare of God, and dye in his fauour: Let the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent men be diſarmed a Gods name, not to giue them cauſe to thinke the better of themſelues, as if they were to be feared, or reputed dangerous and polliticke: but as you take kniues and other hurtfull things from madde men to preuent miſchiefe, that they neither endanger others, nor themſelues: In a word, let all good orders be obſerued, and a faſhion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able body of a religious Common-Wealth erected, that his Maieſties perſon may bee ſecured, the Prince and his Siſter protected and pleaſed, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt neighbours ſubtenated with care and dilligence, out owne Country flouriſhing with proſperity and confidence, the poore releeued, the trades reſtored, the City repayred, the Merchant countenanced, the ſouldiers eſteemed, the Clergy-man beloued, the well deſerued reuerenced, the weake ſupported, the obſtinate ſinner puniſhed, the offender through frailty remitted, and all iuſtifiable actions practiſed to the glory of God, and comfort of our own ſoules.</p>
            <p>Then if there be cauſe of warre,<note place="margin">Exodus 15.1.</note> and ſo ſucceſſe fallen, <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall ſing a ſong of Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph to the Lord; and <hi>Miriam</hi> the Propheteſſe ſhall take a <hi>Timbrell</hi> in her hand, and all the women goe after her with <hi>Timbrels</hi> and Dances: Then if there be the flouriſhes of peace, and that <hi>Salomon</hi> hath finiſhed the Temple of God, and his owne houſe, he will preſent himſelfe before the Lord,<note place="margin">1 Kings 8.22.9</note> and kneele to his prayers, ſpredding foorth his hands toward Heauen: And then to conclude both in war
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:177959:9"/> and peace ſhall <hi>England</hi> confeſſe to the Lord. What is man, that thou ſhouldeſt thinke vpon him, or the ſonne of man, that thou wilt remember him? and ſo prayſe the Lord in his Sanctuary, and in the fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament of his power: prayſe him in his mighty acts, and according to the excellency of his greatneſſe, prayſe him for thinking vpon vs, euen in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar of ſuppreſſing Papiſtry, and baniſhing the Prieſts and Ieſuites.</p>
            <p>I will meddle with no matter of State, nor ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture traducing for ſelfe loue, or aduiſing others more wiſer then my ſelfe, but keepe cloſe to the ſhore of this one ſpeciall obſeruation: Let the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries of religion ſay what they can to accuſe a Proteſtant of one murther, whereas God and the World knowes, that not onely the turbulencies of <hi>Europe</hi> haue beene blowne vp with popiſh breath, and ſufflation of Conſiſtorian Cardinals: but the fearefull ſlaughters of Princes haue beene audaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly proſecuted, eyther by Friers and Prieſts, or ſuch inſtruments, whom the peſtilent Ieſuites haue ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced: what ſtate then in the world (eſpecially our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches, if there were no other cauſe then this affrighting, would endure then in the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and therefore now this muſt needes be a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe to <hi>England,</hi> that at this inſtant ſuch a mercy floweth toward vs, as a Proclamation againſt them.</p>
            <p>How <hi>Geneua</hi> hath continued, and groaned vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the preſſure of many difficulties, yea, endured diuers aſſaults of whole armies, and volleies of ſhot, from the mounted Cannons againſt her; and yet was neuer any attempt made vpon the Duke of <hi>Sauoy,</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:177959:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> and her aduerſaries by her procurement, or ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is well knowne to the world.</p>
            <p>In all thoſe bloody maſſacres of <hi>France,</hi> and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of the ciuell warre, what one miſchiefe was euer conceiued againſt the perſons of their Kings, and who durſt lay hands on the Lords Annoynted? In that fiery triall in the dayes of Queene <hi>Mary,</hi> when the rages of Papiſts made them more furious, then a Beare robbed of her Whelpe: What one Proteſtant ſlipped out of the circle of obedience, to put her in ſuſpition of her life, yea it is well knowne, that the Proteſtants of <hi>Suffolke</hi> aduanced her to the Crowne though they were the firſt that felt the effect of her ingratitude: In all the troubles of <hi>Germany,</hi> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions vpon the free Cities, how ſecurely did the Emperors goe on concerning their owne perſons, and when did you read of a Pope ſlaine, but as they poyſoned one another. I will name but one thing in the Low-Countries, and that is the pride and cruelty of the Duke of <hi>Alua;</hi> ſo that if euer an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe might haue beene made for taking away a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants life, it might here in ſome action or other haue receiued a iuſtifiable forme, and yet <hi>Alua</hi> liued with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out touch, and practiſed all manner of wickedneſſe without controule: whereas on the contrary ſide in theſe Countries formerly mentioned, there hath bin a 1000 ſeuerall murthers committed vpon the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of publicke and priuate perſons, or at leaſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted with reſolution to be actuated vpon aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage by popiſh Prieſts, Ieſuites, and their Officiall, and Miniſters: Is it not high time then to baniſh them our Common-wealth, or doe as we haue done (and ſo it ſhall be no new matter or deuiſe of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment)
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:177959:10"/> euen hang them vp at Tyborne, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude them into the houſe of ſlaughter, where Iuſtice is predominant.</p>
            <p>Marke for Gods ſake, marke the ſecrets of good husbandry, he that meanes to till and manure a wod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ground, muſt leaue no ſtumps within touch, leaſt he breake his plow in the labour, and ſee freſh ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and ſprigs to ſprout vp to choake the corne: the beſt way then is to ſtocke vp roote and tinde, and follow the picke-axe with a ſpade, that the ground may bee throughly ſearched indeede; and ſo muſt <hi>England</hi> doe with this brood of Vipers, eyther pull out their ſtings, or chap them in peeces: For ſo were the Prieſts of <hi>Baal</hi> ſerued at ſeuerall times, and in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall places by <hi>Gedeon, Iohn, Elias, Ioſias,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther godly Prieſts and Princes: but ſeeing this good beginning of our gracious and iudicious King, in the quenching the ſmoake of theſe fire-brands, which in time would eyther haue blinded our eyes, or put them cleane out, hath cheered our hearts, and powred the balme of <hi>Gilead</hi> into our wounds, let him haue the glory of his owne handy-worke, and <hi>England</hi> the joy, and ſo both he, <hi>England,</hi> and euery true Chriſtian retribute all poſſible thankes to the ancient of dayes, whoſe haires are as white as wooll, and eyes as a flame of fire; and to the voyce that commandeth vs out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> leaſt we be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in her abhominations: For <hi>Babylon is fallen, is fallen, that great City; becauſe ſhe made all the nations drinke of the Wine of the wrath of her Fornication.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:177959:10"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
